let's go ahead and assertive mrs
research tools yes eli eight nine five
dash three
either instructor kercher where
i'm wearing lots of
well we're recording devices cousin try
record this for folks who are here
we have at least two people at sea right
now
course
and we also have at least two people
outside antsy calm
following along
from ships in other places
so i'm really trying to record his
lectures and post them
encourage you all if you want bring your
own
recording device either just audio or
audio and video
we have number of students in here who
was english is not their first language
and i encourage you all to record hope
to have one recording right there which
is great
record across well means and use it
however you feel like
in terms of
murray education this this class is open
so if you use the nose or something else
that that's fantastic
amid talk a little bit about
what we're doing here but first mostly
afraid of computers
after his classic please don't go off
and do other stuff on the computer
related to the class
picketers therefore the classic if you
want take notes on the computer that's
great
if you have fun doing busy baseball
i'm in the very upset
by all means use the computers for
note-taking for class
and talk a little bit about the goals
uh... portrayed in the class
who i am
because of who i am with her influence
what material in a show you today
so if you had a different instructor
appear you definitely see a different
set
maybe some overlap maybe not
of materials so you need to know who i
am kind of judgment when i'm teaching
you
animal talk about
savannah material that we're going to
cover during the course
and if we have time
we'll look at the secom wiki and uh...
some of the tools that
going to what we'll do in the course
thursdays and overview
don't feel like if you don't understand
what's going on his just to get you
familiar with terms
to know who i a m and what's about to
happen
don't expect to actually
you come out of his costume a team to do
something new intensive wild
that'll be uh...
upcoming classes will give you those
tools
sony first talk about the goal of the
course
how much are and stay away from power
point not to go too fast
stop me if i'm going to fast if i use
words that i have explained that the
donor stand there is going to be a fair
bit of techno babble during this talk
rather keep it in that you know
what's going on at passwords
has become on the course and then try
and set up a group chat
so you can ask each other if you don't
wanna interrupt me you can ask each
other
if you're feeling unsure of how to ask
questions you've been discussing
occurred chap
well we're going on
i've done that and other places that has
worked pretty well so we'll see how that
will come here because basically
you guys are scientists and you have
computers
those computers often dictate how you
work
and make you work in ways that you don't
want to
so we want ur nose
those were supposed to tools in front of
you
into something that's working for you as
opposed to you being stuck turn survived
this thing in front of you
i would do a little bit here and there
talking about things that are computers
because
paper and pen as a research tool for the
brings a research tool
the person excuse a research to but
we're gonna focused heavily on the
computers
we're gonna try and uh...
build up a community of people working
to get her to attack these goals so
what are we trying to do you do know is
a scientist
you want to collect
anyone to do something with that data so
you want to
process it
and from that process data
you're gonna wanna save it so you can
use it later on other people can use it
so we call that archiving
you're going to want to
external things one here you to read
reports
and this one
if you're taking a summer hydro course
in those
beginning this summer session
you're doing a report
for summer hide your reply was shipped
and this is going to be
one of your key deliverables
you're going to you
also make charts
and maps
use for offers a different things in
europe report you'll have some key
charts and maps
format
you any good people
early papers
which hopefully go off into journals
based on what you come out of this
you gotta go back and
plan to do some more
cruises so if you're at noaa
go out and do you next hydrographic
surveyor for a twenty other had her for
a stations if you are a scientist
you're going to go back and look at the
data have more questions do you want to
look at it a part of the world
so you're gonna play on
and from there
you're going to mobilize another cruise
which are calm on board
globalize adhere to go click more data
and this is a basic
well here
in which
scientific
practical applications here trying to
solve
and the case uh... practical
one example is
mariners
you have people out there driving ships
based on
data you collected gone through some
process
and they're out there driving around a
thousand foot natural gas carrier
based on stuff that
music and you do
that's a pretty big deal
we're talking about data here and the
flow
a part of this is you guys we have
people in here
who are driving this process around
we'll try to give you guys and tools to
do this for us to try to get you to
collaborate so that
you work together down the rest of your
career
you're gonna be in this world whether it
be
i had your had rubber feet or general
marine sciences or maybe even not marine
sciences
our whole peer in this course is that
you start working together you create
working relationships with people that
will
go on past this class so
many of you are going to go back to
other countries afterwards are gonna be
at sea
and you need to work with the community
as a whole to build up those tools
because
i may have and i patted a laptop and
desktop
but i also have the people i met last
year the year before
who may be somewhere else in the world a
different time zone
who i can call on as my tool and say hey
help i've got this problem i know you
saw something like it can you please
work with me
those relationships
will make or break
out your career a lot of times if you've
got them
out you may be the last someone in the
in the election when you're a manic
ocean
hey how'd you fix the whatever ownership
you get an answer and boom off you go if
you think about ships
when you go through all of us
we're talking about
in u_s_ dollars fifty k
up to you know
two hundred thousand dollars
for one day a ship time out there
and if you're fighting tools and fooling
around
with things that are working for you
that's wasted time the picking up in the
ocean we have a
huge world out there who shins lakes
rivers
they'd need mapping and a lot of it
needs mapping again and again have to
see for changes
so we wanted to create this optimize
path
makes people work as effectively as they
can and have a good time doing it
to go out there and spend it with your
life out there map in the world
and doing some really great science
so my hope is in this course and i show
you a whole lot of tools
well help you through this process i
don't expect you to use all of the
schools in your career
but i've succeeded five influenced you
in ways that you like
uh... once you leave here to do better
science and to have
the computer actually help you out more
than it's been doing in the past
so i'm gonna go ahead narrates that's
walk through some of the tools after i
talk about myself but
so no enjoy a really is important in
terms of understanding what i'm showing
you
each person's background will influence
what they've
thousands and thousands of tools out
there
and you don't have time to learn them
also i have more on the mall
so i might be missing stuff that you
find your current fantastic that i
didn't find for my able to something if
that doesn't need my need for them i
mean if you are needs
this is my name on card
i have a website
and on there i have a blog
if you are still without me you can take
a look at that
it's kinda weird
it falls also the ram topics that
they're just follow what i'm feeling
like i'm not one of those people who
applauds only about one topic
this is
really might just sort of work out that
i feel like putting out
and the public
my background i have a
a p_h_d_ and bachelors and they're in
geology
for my bachelors
that's not the ocean this was a
land-based geology degree
out my p_h_d_
was in
paley lag
crazy word
extricate your fee
mapping the continental slopes
the tolerate
i didn't do a whole lot of computers and
that's tough why wouldn't the geology
a computer was used to write a paper
with word
and
when i asked to do some processing how
to do it the professors that to me like
i was crazy
you go through the microscope you did
you hear of your field notes
everybody carried around
something like
fax approval to bigger fairfield
geologist
and you are everything in here
and if anybody else in this room one of
my notes they had to come to me a pass
so that drove me crazy
might beginnings of research tools was
these are really great and that's a lot
of a slight paper and pencil
people cancelled really hard to share
yet i find it skinner three are handed
off someone hope it comes back
how yet he's a photocopier
you're gonna find when i'm teaching that
you're gonna find influences from
i worked at carnegie mellon is a
computer scientist
and i work in stamford
in the nineteen nineties
so you're gonna see
a lot of tools that were popular and
this time period
that are still
being used
and in fact
almost every computer in here house
stuff
hi actually touched way back when
not very much
little bits here and there
they're going to show you are all things
are typically been around
for ten twenty thirty years and i expect
to be around for another ten twenty
thirty years
i did learn
prachi i guess
backgrounds called park in full
eighteen ninety
i learned from the looks very different
from what he did
and i can use about five percent of my
knowledge on that
it's nothing like
g_i_s_ is today
i had no idea
how do you start yesterday taking
classes and not
an expert in
parks here see that
you know i did all the stuff
and i don't know
how to use our at all
muniz god
be surprised by that
my work at the u_s_ g_s_
and some of my software
is still running
at the u_s_ g_s_ doing i'm not sure what
this is all stuff that doesn't have
anything to do with that so
ice pack tools like that to change
and a way that media which did ten years
ago
doesn't really help if you use word
twenty years ago and you know you backed
up word today
and by attorneys for two thousand seven
on the pc i get very confused
have also spent a lot of time at nasa
so you're gonna see a lot of stuff that
i do
is not necessarily a lot of marine
scientists do i'm trying to combine the
best of all of these worlds where i saw
stuff
at nasa on space craft
how can we use those same techniques
and see
for our datasets
uh... different data
same ideas in terms of processing
and i just spent
a month ago
and uh... i did a lot of step with the
uh... earth in the ocean city md six a
year and i find that
i throw in a lot of extra little stuff
for him
google earth emotions dual fusion tables
uh... feel their school that
so don't be surprised to hear that and
you can take it as well they actually
paid me
do you know that i took money from them
so that's a bias that i have been always
beware m
you know what people are doing where
they came from
but and i thought that was shocking to
the topics and i'm gonna show you a
whole pile of stuff
and a lot of that is going to be
gibberish to you the idea is not that
you understand what is but just to start
seeing the words
happy as you can google
and star becoming just familiar with
vocabulary because there's a lot
it's gonna take repetition of really
working on these things throughout the
semester
right the first thing
primary
break through the whole course
is a little bit surprising
and it's security
nobody likes to have their computer
hacker get a virus or have trouble
so i'm a triumph of sizes throughout the
course of his
when is a tool okay here's what is it
not ok to use
working this all over the place with
government and industry
if the software is gonna get you hacked
he can't find a way around it
you can't use it
we're gonna have to talk about security
and making sure your passenger safety
and i think you things
about how to security
and to secure login at that stage
and
of virtual private network
dpm
zero
acronyms
will go through what they are as we get
there
for now i'm not gonna go into much more
neither one is passwords
i'm gonna show you how to safely store a
lot of passwords and use a different
passport on every single thing that you
do
without going crazy
if you can't do this kind of stuff
if you use that little notebook if you
want your passwords here
and you lose it
because if he gets wet
because of the fire whatever happens to
it
that sucks
so how do you have something where
you can have all your passwords
and if someone gets that file with all
your passwords it is in a plain text
file i ran off with all
all of your work and you know that your
home computer operator tax information
and you get very unhappy
not very exciting but it makes the world
around being able to do things safely
more exciting is were actually going to
go and use
something called one x
which is an operating system much like
windows except for its less focused on
the graphical aspect of things
rugged a run
what's called a command line
with a tool called bashed
which stands for the born again shell
and this is going to be
your command line
the idea being that if you have to type
something
imagine document retrain described how
in photoshop
you tweak one image you are just the
collars you are a crop it
out maybe remove the redeye you do ten
or fifteen different things
that's ok we need to take a screenshot
of each one
but what if you have ten thousand images
that you need to process any need to do
it every power
or ratings on the command line
you have step one step to step three
step four
you can put those into a file you have a
very clear description of what you've
done if you run those commands
you'll get exactly same result every
time
if u dragging click in photoshop
jim might get the same thing they might
not
we've had trouble trying to reproduce
like
collar bouncing
where we have two different people who
slightly treat this lighter a little bit
differently and suddenly end up with
on repeatable scientific results
so far not
we have a concept of
repeatable
research
you know what your permian whiteboard
there's no spell check up here so i get
in trouble
so i apologize for any uh...
misspellings
but what if you know research the idea
is if i go out and do something
i process the data and i handed over the
next person
they should be able to take my data
and do exactly what i did without a lot
hassle
and not to find all give you guys a link
to that there's different
ratings for forgettable research
and the harder it is for someone
repeated the lower down the scale of the
people researcher debts
so if i can often next person and they
can do exactly what i didn't
within you know ten fifteen minutes
minus that time it appeared crunched on
the debt
that's fabulous
if i could ever looked at standard
he'll retire
and that's the goal is not a perfect
thing but that's where we're trying to
head towards
how are we gonna run most because all
these computers in front of you run
windows
we don't really want to go fiddle with
system settings in
and stuff like that so we're going to
you something called a virtual
machine
orpheum
and what that is is
you'll download a file
that file is like the whole operating
inside of the program
i've got a mac here you've got windows
two outdoor ad your computer's bills if
they can make a point here
and i'm gonna show you
this window thomas mack
is running one x
so i'm gonna go ahead and
at my password
and that's limits
in a little window running on how
macintosh
acting copy that file to anyone of you
and you'll be able to do exactly the
same thing in that little window you can
stall software you could break it
whenever it doesn't matter because just
a file an appeal today you can delete it
and get their original back for me
so the ideas that will be playing inside
of this and it it blows up on you if you
scripts and configuration
about a leaky needed to lead on the
virtual machine and get the file again
and start over
right now are virtual machine may not
mean very much to you uh... but will
start using them
i think you guys are going to really
like them because you can take them home
with you on a usb stick
and put them into different here
and start working again with the exact
same environment
without having to shuffle around lots of
stuff and install software everytime
city ideas
this is uh... a little
playpen we can work inside a that's a
lot safer than the normal computers in
both the windows machine
you have to go to the idea is
annemarie windows machine for a couple
days as they try and figure out what you
did to it or start from scratch
and it might take them a little while
this way
if things go wrong we don't care we just
deleted and we start over
the next thing is
we need to pay for and they were
collected at you pretty much have to
have a programming language in your belt
it doesn't really
matter where it is if you're really good
some of the current things that we don't
cover in this course that's fantastic
bankers you keep with it
but we're gonna take a programming
language that's going to work pretty
well for us i think
and that's called pipeline
this is a away we can describe commands
and processes that we're going to you
we're not going to get into it all heavy
duty like a computer scientist
we're gonna use it as scientists so just
enough to get the job done
graphs charts to collect a debt
do we need to do we're gonna do
from early with i thought
it's going to be our toolkit of
and get in there
crabs and a half figure out what it is
and get did our job done
why pipeline
that's a great question
there's lots of languages like a classic
one the people learn beginning is called
c_
if we're going to see
it would be about three months before we
could do anything useful
to open a file what not
matlab is another great tool
super powerful
he requires a license
attends to push you over the way from
nice coating style so the code you're
gonna raise in the a lot harder for
began to read
this cost is really high
uh... someone from the people can for
sure take with them
icon will be with you for the rest your
life
if the company does not live goes out of
business
urinal
and there's a lot of other once in a
fine people learn fortran
i had to learn for training enter my
brain swiss cheese enemy cramping
python intends to be a nice balance of
easy to do
very easy to read
lots of scientific data
capabilities
but it's not dealing with your lots of
good ones like
matlab is actually a great tool you can
do it on the signs with the ill find a
lot of people in this building is not
lab
but for us
this is something that will be with you
for the rest your life if you want it
there's a little bonus if you start yes
scripts something in our ta s
pythons language that they use inside
so it's pretty handy in terms of that
i'd like to build you guys tools and of
course that that would work with park
g_i_s_ very nicely in the end without
actually doing arts yes in this course
does a great tool for being in that mail
making things go
zero dollars line
is awfully nice
it's not perfect
and you may find yourself and you were
things and you'll see that we use little
tiny bits boeing which is
and will be just enough to get by
and won't do anymore than we need to as
the attorney fees to cover but
it's a nice life
the next thing rent due is a little
scary to some but
don't be scared by this it's structured
query
language
or ask you elem
this is the language of databases
we are going to u only as much as we
need to tear tip store some data
this is like the spreadsheet with the
f_b_i_ data worlds
but it's a little bit easier to follow
them what's going on excel spreadsheet
i've watched two people
get nailed by that
i clicked on what cell and what happened
problem
and spreadsheets
but this is a great where do you can
pass data between
all sorts of different tools
all of these tools right here
all carried a layout of the database so
this is the language of databases
i don't want you to become experts in it
if you do that's great
but i want you know just enough that
this doesn't scare you at the end
and that if you want to put in their
database
and pass it around
it's a great way to pass there because
it knows about what columns called white
and is a really nice database called ask
you
light
this database
it's not very powerful but doesn't not
that we need it
and has this great property of
most databases like to get work only
after i get a database administrator you
gotta pay the person is
peter every year
we have to do with you'd always
complicate things
ask you like is a file
is sort of in a false you know about the
server from sore learnings and database
thingyan be scary
as he was something that will play with
and when i showed you the first time it
won't look like much failed to state use
in the background
it's inside of firefox
if you're in firefox ins machines it's
right there
it's it's hiding behind the scenes and
everything it's actually
the most common database in the world
this has about delano hundred
esculent databases on it
despina a cell phone
so it's it's actually everywhere in the
beyond the ship's it'll be
in your pocket on the phone
and it's just hey you know this
and is a really great tool
esculent
manager
and the best part is this the firefox
plugin
in your browser
and you run this their nature davis look
like a spreadsheet
so it it'll be like a very simple
assault spreadsheet
but then you can go take that they're
right over to fight on to other stuff
anything lower inter arc g_i_s_ you can
do all kinds of things with this data
and you can work would just like a
spread sheet that you can actually go
and see the raw behind the scenes
whereas if you open up
microsoft is excel spreadsheet you're
going to the king it's really horrible
confusing stuff
told to just a little bit databases
we're gonna talk about something
everywhere now and you have to face this
when you go on right
your final report and submit your data
for archiving
extensible
markup
language
this is a way
to take taxed
and if it blocks around various things
and say what does this mean so
if i have
the document i could put a block around
some time to say this is the title
i have put a block remote
push attack to say this is the location
uh... this is the description paragraph
and it's got these tags you wrap around
things he mark things up
so if you get really crazy complicated
we're gonna stay away from the
complicated stuff but the key thing is
is that
if you need to make highest so
meditative
to present here like a bunch of groans
from the room at this point
meditate is not very exciting to most
people
i had so many of his in excel format
and there's lots of other
types of formats that are built on x_
amount
the great thing is that there's really
nice tools and placed on and off the
languages to reach in there
and to work with the stuff so you don't
have to open up and read it by hand
which you can do but
there's a lot of little angle bracket
characters running around everywhere
they're kinda
turn you bring the swiss cheese
work a little bit with dot and want to
take maybe a
from files and uses
i know most people just create met in
throwing out there and hope that does
something useful
who were going to load in
a whole lot of no data
and you're going to use that to make
some graphs so
if you have something called a bag
about the ashby degrade
you can go in there
pull outs that xa momenta data
and then
from there you can look inside that
night and we'll tell you the bounding
box about data on the planet earth
and so somewhere out there
is this little box you wanna put on the
globe
and the best part is i grabbed one of
these
an archive site open up the file grab
made a a plot of it
and this was from a high directly
institution in applied in the middle of
canada
right on land
this effort has meant real well but it's
super powerful and can help us go check
there something wrong
that bag or the saw for the created
that put that data that should have done
in the gulf of mexico
up in
decaying arctic
being able to take this stuff make a
quick plot of victims quickly show you
am i doing
everything right through my tool chain
or if someone gives you a destroyer of
full of three terra bytes of data
fairly typical number for today's
usb drives
as full of these
tea bag files
where are they
you were at that point was survey
numbers are just a number you have no
idea and last year
deeply ingrained in a revision that made
that file
where it's from
so by being a reduced medea
and create some visualization out of it
really quickly didn't go figure out what
kind did in my facing isn't the right
data that i wanted
and how do we put together
good thing is is that where do a lot of
text-based material
so i'm gonna get you to use a text edits
unlike everything the tvs before i'm
sure
it's called
you max
demat sizzle was an unusual bees to fish
so much fun showing that
i know maybe
a fraction of one percent of what it's
capable of
this is a tech so that if you do you
want it
will last you your entire lifetime
making to you
super powerful stuff
origin write a letter to your mom
it will play tetris
it will do all kinds of crazy stuff
but this is something that if you are in
this it's great fraying
software thirty writing python code it's
great
if you want to open up on these external
documents it will do that nicely
it's something that i've served in using
and nineteen ninety nine
and it's only gotten better
and it's about the same
as it was back then in terms of
interface so anything you learn in this
now
will be kid for another twenty years at
least
how you compares alternate alternatives
ultra simple
you max
has gotten easier to use but it's super
powerful take awhile to get into the
features
speaking to you everything authentic and
and more
as a part of this there's a system
called or grodin
for taking notes they keeping track of
things
i touched up planning before
and falling through or mode is away
that you can take notes and unlike
microsoft word
it's a flat tax thing
so if you want to have a title
you just right
a star
the space
your title the section
you can write us with any tech center so
if you were working on strategy could
write that
anything with start space and then
syntax becomes your title about section
and you document
it's called the markup language
kind of i got snow but a lot simpler
and what that does
is let's work with other tools so we
think that microsoft word document
it's really hard to take a word document
and start passing around other other
tools
how does that ritual ask your word
document go grab all citizens are stuff
were all my notes located
geographically or timelines
boris version
cut on its own it can lead to document
indecent stuff like that but
this gives us the way we can actually
put source code in there
so if you have a little bit of python
script that you want to have in your
documents as i do it
you can actually select that code and
save money
right from inside that
a document
will also produce
p_b_s_ for u so if you are most pbf of
your notes
if you want to have a web page
in our language called html
it will do that for you
if you want to the source to be at a
table data and sort of uh... journals
file thing there's something called late
at that will book at a little bit
and i think is a little complicated but
wicked or go to al put all these
different formats
and it will do a lot more
this is what about it
a really great waited to handle building
notes and imagining ownership
when something went wrong and you have
five or six people working throughout
the ship at all times
how do you correlate the notes between
everybody saying this for a was doing
something different on the ship that
time
and they all had impact on
some problem that happened with the
sonar
and somebody was working on the g_p_s_
in with the antenna by accident
now wire was cut here and so valentine
signatures marketing and the sonar
how do you correlate that
with this it's almost the database so
you can ask for mode if you had
everybody's files linked together
all right let's go grab rails from
everybody in this role
and we'll see what happened
and i respect her dot on the ship black
family bought the g_p_s_ in a couple
more into it
so you can start figuring out from all
those notes and correlations
what happened in a survey and land
and uh... when you're on shore two years
later trying to figure out what went
wrong
this kinda stuff can be supercritical
for example someone
took a core
from the ocean
copy-cat dropped on the debt for example
that means in my p_h_d_ thesis back or
no longer works because you've
jiggle the briefing in that core
i can't use it for my thesis butt
i found cases where people never wrote
that down
they never took notes
or was in paper and i couldn't get
linkedin sis is a nice way
uh... in the work
you don't use the maximum loan tenure
from now it's just a text file
i think you can read start title is
taxed
most people and be able to read
breakthrough as if you're just waiting
regular english
i apologize not knowing how good it is
with foreign languages
will have to see
for those of you who right now on
non latin characters it may get a little
challenging right
i think people giving to charities
imax
mortals we're gonna talk about
something called the attack
this is a wine which of journal
references
when you find some information that you
think is important to hear the writing
about down the road
midtech is a place you can put that you
can we get in
through tools called uh... jab ref
answer terra
and even if you want if you want you can
actually take references you put
into your database
and make the right into your marks
upward document for your sticking with
microsoft word
so when you go undercover for the class
you can take those references
and just going to them in word and when
you can reference section i will do
everything correctly
if you're in uh... george bush on turkey
for example you'll take in canada
correctly
and then uh...
when your paper comes out and you site
kena in your paper
at the write-up can't with all the right
to use it
and then to partner will be very happy
when i know
and note is a powerful tool
buds these tools do you just as well as
i know it most tasks
and it's expensive
when we tried to customize it and do
things with it dot berry frustrating we
did some amazingly cool customers asians
in research tools
eleven issues and did my hand
has been the lustrous
runner of this class for many years and
trying to fill the shoes
dave and i had to cost you privately and
no and it was very powerful and it gets
the job done
counter was badly
it's simpler
there's certain things
doesn't have as many
journal
styles and things like that and i'll
as an it does
the terrorist pretty powerful
a lot of schools have just switched
completely over to the terror
this runs as a firefox plugin
so if your honor webpage
and you want to create an entry in your
database of journal references
is he really great paper on multan
solaris
he has hit the button at the bottom pet
enters into database
and no can do that but it's kind of this
thing that runs around
you have to act
bolted on after the fact
piano folks who tried to get them
to clobber professor
can succeed
we're gonna look at version control with
text files sewer look at something
called mercurial
otherwise known by the uh... symbol of
the elements
benefit version control
if you've seen track changes
in microsoft word this is like that but
if all of us in this room one write a
paper together
this would let us all corroborate at the
same time n_-word overseeing this
together
whereas with word i have yet to find
someone is able to
really work on the same document same
time
have the changes merged together cleanly
this leads people
work on very large
any tax or binary file you want to
passed them around
and managed
files
of any sort
over the long run
if you ever go back and say that you
know what
i really don't like what i've done right
now i need to go back to last week
this will still have it
so if you committed a change
to a document
and you wanna go back to it you can do
that you can list all the changes
if two people have worked on the same
file you want to compare how they're
doing it
you can basically brings and say okay
how did
has ads in bob's versions compare
it's a really powerful tool and this is
what secom is trying to use
for its revision control
software and taxed
and even throw in
binary date if you felt like it's not
super great with binary data but it
could handle it
so is the sort of her
archive store of things and how to share
files
were actually going to use an service
called pickpocket
which is kind of a goofy name
where you guys can collaborate when
you're working on research tools
you'll each be able to have a bit but
that account
you can give each other permission
ordered perot croatia and you've been
submit bugs on each other's work
so if if somebody's working on a
particular scripted say handle some part
of both needed a prostitute
you guys can copy that your own
workspace change it
and then
suggested changes back you can do all
sorts of stuff like that
he uses the flickr real
system in here
in a walk you through the whole process
of being able to manage files
tracked changes and share them with here
your colleagues
eyes really amazing that you can do
actually had some i've never met
fix a bug in my software suggested to me
and within about two minutes of the
suggestions in my email
i said i looked at it it and showed to
me said this was changing
do you want to keep this or not they
said yes and when and
and about me michael runaway
some i don't know where the guy who was
in the world
it's an amazing way to be able to share
stuff you can also be stuff privately
we're slower pickpocket blessing about
this material is that if you want to
stop using it you just stop and you can
end point
you consider data somewhere else that
you just tell it where i want to push
the issue
so it's really flexible
of course that's what to do is they
require a little bit more fought in
terms of
you guys figuring out how it works but
will go through that slowly
we're gonna talk about traditional
things that might be used to hearing
about
g_m_t_
generic mapping tools
we're going to make some absolute g_m_t_
this is that
the classical fan of a beautiful map
it's really pretty map it might be a
little hard to make sometimes
it makes a great
there's also a tool
called andy
system
that reads more fitting data we'll take
a look at that it actually you g_m_t_
and we'll do some things like without
whereas are both in data file from in
will get a cool track plot out by the
file
you could do a little bit their
processing air
this is what i sort of say
start looking at carrots or high pack
or
foot arouse
something like that fear both india
crossing across the state in here
it's doable
but it's not
super efficient
but you can do things like craig
automatic maps that
degenerate every kind of any data file
for multi make it on that they build you
a map of the area
with it the optimal team merged in there
it's really powerful tool
that's great for doing automatic stuff
happens
also talk about
consider purchasing a search has off
with q g_i_s_
this is a tool better actually
scales amazingly
it's really simple it's called doc
watson g_i_s_
it doesn't have a
every feature on the planet
because i'm a small fraction of what in
our g_i_s_
but you can plug in python
i've seen people to you
absolutely amazing stuff with this
and it's free
and it comes with length so you'll just
get keyed years you can also install of
windows
answered yes to all you could have
looking for the rest your career it's
free
and it's always there
dot already may end up looking at
r_j_r_'s for some other tasks
just because this
this is open source and there's not a
huge commercial driving force behind it
so
it doesn't
the surge as many features just jammed
into it
we're gonna look at will call do you
know
or you might hear pal sometimes brutal
geospatial
data
abstraction library
this is the handy dandy swiss army knife
of converting formats so someone gives
you a geospatial format acts in you want
geospatial format
this is that all you want
it can read a marine chart and that's
fifty seven
an output ideal or
in one line
code to want to see me simply just copy
and paste needs someone gives you that
chorten says please visualize what's in
this new chart
along with that
in her sciences and
also for me in
mar sciences
projections
are a moral pain there are tens of
thousands of projections in common usage
it really is
painful some news
there's a library called proj four
and if you want to convert from some
production some projection
this tool party knows not all the
projections and we'll do it for you but
quickly
sold to some examples of projecting data
so going beyond two from
geographic d_d_t_ alum
it gets really great for that
it's actually inside of
things like flare-ups a lot of tools use
proj
do their projections
i'm not sure if
i think it's a all the tools like
nobody's there's some really great tools
out there that have proj hiding in the
background
it's super eighty was written by the
u_s_ g_s_ way back when by their
projections fears
has been taken over and including the
interest
playa i'm that the same guy who wrote
to go back to my little girl went
in terms of google will be using earth
has a nice display part for me it's
super easy
it doesn't always as possible as we'd
like but if you want to just put up some
lines are image on the globe it's
fantastic
will show you how to make
visualization into north in just a
couple minutes if you get new data it's
a great way just to see what's around
if we have time near the end of semester
there's something called fusion tables
and you can take
database type stuff
and this is a cloud database
where you can once the date is in here
if somebody wants a shared it with you
you can merge each other's did together
and create combined maps
is pretty fancy if you're not has
geospatial information if you say please
show it to me on the google map
so it's a matthew please make a deal a
map of this data
i don't know how to do that
i know how to put my dating to hear and
hit the map button
so it's a and i see anyway have
sharing publicly datasets
and combining stuff
i put the u_s_ coast guard
incident database which is when
incidents analyzing accidents
so if you wonder correlates
yeah ship incidents with some feature on
charts
you lit up a table of all the chart that
you want
anthony could
merge it with my
fusion table of
incidents
and you could use some correlation
analysis things like that
to offset this is is this is not
a free program is free isn't cheap is
utterly open-source thing route we count
on google for this one
there's also nasa world wind
which reads the same file format is
cooler so we can share data
and therefore stratton at nasa world
wind
use that a few years that a big
appointed be back in june
really more important than all of that i
think it is
one technology that i want you guys to
experience
is usually associate with locating pack
computers
but it's actually a really great tools
cult paranoia really chat
imagine a world
wherever using some software
you wellness program you pick the chair
of bus offering to talk to the guy who
prove it
that's what this is
it support
actual developers of software hang out
and you can go jump in the conversation
and ask the
the person who actually did the work
would you do what i can you help me fix
something when i do wrong
it's a really wild and crazy place in
terms of
be with you support in real time
nothing you can do is you can set up
aversion of this on your shit
and you can have a group chat
partnership
the doesn't go outside of the ship so if
you felt like
if you're a really big survey shipping
you got
in fifty or sixty people run around the
ship some work on the bridge summer down
below summer stateroom
this the way you can occur chuck
ownership set up yourself
be able to
to have all of the things that the files
you can't easily great stuff summer have
you guys use that as the chat
inside the classroom
we're going to look at wikis
where you actually save notes and part
of form we have a wiki info ccom
so on thursday will go ahead and look at
the uh... the wiki
and start making some changes
combining
the wiki plus my receipt
away do you guys can keep collaborating
once you leave here
it doesn't matter where in the world you
are
as long as you can get some internet
uh... which isn't always easy on the
ship
but as long as you've gone back you guys
can keep cooperating for the rest of
your careers
if you guys are developing your own
specialities you guys can work together
in teams
matter where you are
and tell you my email pulling off a
cross-country boundaries
it makes the world a very small place
back up cuz i got my list of order along
with google earth enough to worry when
that there is a key cool
at will help you get into those two
and that is
geo
which is done akumar doherty
if we can pull it off we're going to
have won a guy from the team
for m_g_m_ ap ap
and arguably come up here and give you
guys talking shit you hal
this is god
a global database of some amazing
pollution graphic and geologic data
for the world's oceans
and this is a place if you want to find
some data as a great place to start to
try and find it
it's got ship tracks from
not every crews but every cruiser those
guys confined put in their is in there
so if you're trying to work on a kicker
part of the ocean
this is a great starting point who
worked for finding and out working with
data
multi bean chorus set
grab samples you name it in all kinds of
stuff in there
and in the last thing is
i'm going to have you guys actually work
on data collections here actually gonna
collect
i was hoping today dot she plans her
first example but
not quite year there yet
but we have a a weather station on the
roof
it spits out format called
might look like you to you right now
it's a lot of weird characters
but working away a little python scripts
to grab that data in real time
savers who file seer logging the data as
you would for a and science project
you can then use papon
to pull apart that they'd every
formatted and plot it
with tool called
and you're actually going to log it
over the network when there's something
called p_c_p_
and you d_p_ which you'll need to know
renown but
disparate throws down the annual slowly
gets no them over the next
a couple months
missus actually network protocols you're
gonna grab dinner right off the sensor
over the secom network
when i first sorties in python this
kinda stuff was really hard for me to
you i had to do it
and lots of coverage with me
three or four months to write my first
won the crowd and officially over the
network
with papon
why do you do not have a few minutes
tonight can made by notes map tempelsman
so it's actually fairly easy to grab
this data
and you'll be able to pluck i'll show
you next time a crack legislated
of to hurricane the came through here
so we can grab him watch the pressure go
up and down the commodity temperature
and wind speed
and all that
and duelist within python and will only
be a few lines of code
so it's actually fairly easy dual stuff
to make use of all these tools
anaconda
giddy idea of how it goes rescinded all
the report
archive all of your muscles
so that's the general just out foreign
aid for this course
don't expect
to have to know all the details of
anything when trying to be staying
fairly
independent
so if you get stuck up on databases
will give you
which he did over the next time so that
you can just enough all along
but i want to be comfortable with all
the stuff so that we go to your research
you can pull them out the tool box
hopefully have it in a work more for you
and less
you looking for it
because we've all been abused by
grumpy computers
and an excess crappy
hoping that you guys will get a lot of
this class is more about you
than anything else dot can you guys the
tools to go attack your classes and your
future research
more weapons
that's it for today
next time we'll get arnold will
surrender virtual machine
two guys we'll actually see lennox in
person
will play along with the wiki
blast through any computer problems to
get in our way